{
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Context_Free_Language",
  "duration": 136,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Context_Free_Language",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(G_1, G_2 \\) be Context-Free Grammars (CFGs) and \\(R \\) be a regular expression. For a grammar \\(G \\), let \\(L(G) \\) denote the language generated by \\(G \\).\n<br>\nWhich ONE among the following questions is decidable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = L(G_2) \\)?</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) \\cap L(G_2) = \\emptyset \\)?</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = L(R) \\)?</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = \\emptyset \\)?</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = \\emptyset \\)?</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460820/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following two languages over the alphabet \\(\\{a, b, c\\}\\), where \\(m\\) and \\(n\\) are natural numbers:\n<br><br>\n\\(L_1 = \\{ a^m b^m c^{m+n} \\mid m, n \\geq 1 \\}\\)<br>\n\\(L_2 = \\{ a^m b^n c^{m+n} \\mid m, n \\geq 1 \\}\\)\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the following statements is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both \\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are context-free languages.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is a context-free language but \\(L_2\\) is not a context-free language.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not a context-free language but \\(L_2\\) is a context-free language.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) are context-free languages.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not a context-free language but \\(L_2\\) is a context-free language.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460045/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-35#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following context-free grammar \\(G\\), where \\(S\\), \\(A\\), and \\(B\\) are the variables (non-terminals), \\(a\\) and \\(b\\) are the terminal symbols, \\(S\\) is the start variable, and the rules of \\(G\\) are described as:\n<br><br>\n\\(S \\to aaB \\mid Abb\\)<br>\n\\(A \\to a \\mid aA\\)<br>\n\\(B \\to b \\mid bB\\)\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the languages \\(L(G)\\) is accepted by \\(G\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^2b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\} \\cup \\{ a^n b^2 \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^n b^{2n} \\mid n \\geq 1 \\} \\cup \\{ a^{2n} b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^n b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^{2n} b^{2n} \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^2b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\} \\cup \\{ a^n b^2 \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460071/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements is/are CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The intersection of two regular languages is regular.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The intersection of two context-free languages is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursive languages is recursive.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursively enumerable languages is recursively enumerable.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The intersection of two regular languages is regular.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursive languages is recursive.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursively enumerable languages is recursively enumerable.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399298/gate-cse-2023-question-14#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages:<br><br>\\( \\begin{aligned}\nL_1&amp;= \\{ ww|w  \\in  \\{a,b \\}^* \\}   \\\\\nL_2&amp;= \\{a^nb^nc^m | m,n \\geq 0 \\}  \\\\\nL_3 &amp;= \\{a^mb^nc^n|m,n \\geq 0 \\}\n\\end{aligned}\\)<br><br>Which of the following statements is/are FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not context-free but \\(L_2\\) and \\(L_3\\) are deterministic context-free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_2,L_3\\) and \\(L_2 \\cap L_3\\) all are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor its complement is context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_2,L_3\\) and \\(L_2 \\cap L_3\\) all are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor its complement is context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371898/Gate-cse-2022-question-38#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages:<br><br>\\( \\begin{aligned}\nL_1&amp;= \\{a^n wa^n|w  \\in  \\{a,b \\}^* \\}   \\\\\nL_2&amp;= \\{wxw^R | w,x  \\in   \\{a,b \\}^*, |w|,|x|  \\gt 0  \\}\n\\end{aligned}\\)<br><br>Note that \\(w^R\\) is the reversal of the string \\(w\\). Which of the following is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are regular.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\)  are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\)  are context-free but not regular.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are regular.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\)  are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371899/Gate-cse-2022-question-37#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>For a string \\(w\\), we define \\(w^R\\) to be the reverse of \\(w\\). For example, if \\(w=01101\\) then \\(w^R=10110\\).\n<br>\nWhich of the following languages is/are context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxw^Rx^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{ ww^Rxx^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxx^Rw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{ ww^Rxx^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxx^Rw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357499/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-41#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L_1\\) be a regular language and \\(L_2\\) be a context-free language. Which of the following languages is/are context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap \\overline{L_2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{\\overline{L_1} \\cup \\overline{L_2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup (L_2 \\cup \\overline{L_2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((L_1 \\cap L_2) \\cup (\\overline{L_1} \\cap L_2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{\\overline{L_1} \\cup \\overline{L_2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup (L_2 \\cup \\overline{L_2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((L_1 \\cap L_2) \\cup (\\overline{L_1} \\cap L_2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357528/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-12#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that \\(L_1\\) is a regular language and \\(L_2\\) is a context-free language. Which one of the following languages is NOT necessarily context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cap L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cdot L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 - L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cup L_2\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 - L_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357451/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages. <br>\\(L_1=\\{wxyx|w,x,y \\in (0+1)^+\\}\\) <br>\\(L_2=\\{xy|x,y \\in (a+b)^*,|x|=|y|,x\\neq y\\}\\) <br> <br>Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) context- free but not regular and \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) context- free but  \\(L_2\\) is not context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333199/gate2020-cs-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider the language \\(L=\\{a^n|n\\geq 0\\}\\cup \\{a^nb^n|n\\geq 0\\}\\) and the following statements. <br><br>\nI. L is deterministic context-free.<br>\nII. L is context-free but not deterministic context-free.<br>\nIII. L is not LL(k) for any k.<br><br>\nWhich of the above statements is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333221/gate2020-cs-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following languages over \\(\\Sigma =\\{a,b\\}\\) is NOT context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{ww^R|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nb^nw^R|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nw^Rb^n|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^nb^i|i \\in \\{n,3n,5n\\},n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nw^Rb^n|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302817/gate2019-cs-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages: <br><br>I. \\( \\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|m+p=n+q, \\; where \\;  m,n,p,q \\geq 0 \\}\\)    <br>  II. \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|m=n \\; and \\; p=q, \\; where \\;  m,n,p,q\\geq 0 \\}  \\) <br> III. \\( \\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|m=n=p \\; and \\; p\\neq q, \\; where \\; m,n,p,q\\geq 0 \\} \\) <br>  IV. \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|mn=p+q, \\; where\\;  m,n,p,q\\geq 0\\}\\) <br><br>Which of the languages above are context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204109/gate2018-35#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages<br><br> \\(L_{1}=\\{a^{p}|p\\) is a prime number} <br>\\(L_{2}=\\{a^{n}b^{m}c^{2m}|n\\geq 0,m\\geq 0\\} \\)<br> \\(L_{3}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}c^{2n}|n\\geq 0\\}\\)<br>\\( L_{4}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}|n\\geq 1\\}\\)<br><br> Which of the following are CORRECT ?<br><br>\nI.\\(L_{1}\\) is context-free but not regular. <br>\nII. \\(L_{2}\\) is not context-free. <br>\nIII. \\(L_{3}\\) is not context-free but recursive. <br>\nIV. \\(L_{4}\\) is deterministic context-free. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I ,II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118615/gate2017-2-40#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L_{1},L_{2}\\) be any two context free languages and R be any regular language. Then which of\nthe following is/are CORRECT ?<br> I. \\(L_{1}\\cup L_{2}\\) is context - free <br>II. \\(\\bar{L_{1}}\\)  is context - free <br>III. \\(L_{1} - R\\) is context - free <br> IV. \\(L_{1}\\cap L_{2} \\) is context - free <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I, II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118143/gate2017-2-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages over the alphabet \\(\\Sigma = \\{a, b,c\\}\\). <br>Let \\(L_{1}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}c^{m}|m,n\\geq 0\\}\\) and \\(L_{2}=\\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{n}|m,n\\geq 0\\}\\)<br><br> Which of the following are context-free languages ?  <br>   I. \\(L_{1}\\cup L_{2}\\)  <br>       II. \\(L_{1}\\cap L_{2}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and II</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118321/gate2017-1-38#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>Consider the context-free grammars over the alphabet {a,b,c} given below. S and T are non-terminals <br><br>\\(G_{1}:S\\rightarrow aSb|T, T\\rightarrow cT|\\epsilon\\) \\(G_{2}:S\\rightarrow bSa|T,T\\rightarrow cT|\\epsilon\\) <br><br>The language \\(L(G_{1})\\cap L(G_{2})\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Finite.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Not finite but regular.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Context-free but not regular.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Recursive but not context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Not finite but regular.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118320/gate2017-1-37#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>\\(S \\rightarrow a S a|b S b| a \\mid b\\)<br>The language generated by the above grammar over the alphabet {a,b} is the set of: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>all palindromes</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>all odd length palindromes</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>strings that begin and end with the same symbol</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>all even length palindromes</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>all odd length palindromes</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1304/gate2009-12-isro2016-37\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 19,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages: <br>\\(L_{1}=\\{a^{n}b^{m}c^{n+m}:m,n\\geq 1\\}\\)<br> \\(L_{2}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}c^{2n}:n\\geq 1\\}\\) <br>Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both L1 and L2 are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 is context-free while L2 is not context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L2 is context-free while L1 is not context-free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither L1 nor L2 is context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 is context-free while L2 is not context-free.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39605/gate2016-2-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 20,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following types of languages: \\(L_{1}\\):Regular, \\(L_{2}\\):Context-free, \\(L_{3}\\):Recursive, \\(L_{4}\\):Recursively enumerable. <br>Which of the following is/are TRUE? <br>\nI. \\(\\bar{L}_{3}\\cup L_{4}\\) is recursivelyenumerable<br>\nII. \\(\\bar{L}_{2}\\cup L_{3}\\) is recursive <br>\nIII. \\(L_{1}^{*}\\cup L_{2}\\) is context-free <br>\nIV. \\(L_{1}\\cup \\bar{L}_{2}\\) is context-free <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I, II and III only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I, II and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39574/gate2016-2-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 21,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following languages are context-free? <br>\\(L_{1}=\\{a^{m}b^{n}a^{n}b^{m}|m,n\\geq 1\\}\\) <br>   \\(L_{2}=\\{a^{m}b^{n}a^{m}b^{n}|m,n\\geq 1\\}\\) <br>  \\(L_{3}=\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m=2n+1\\}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 and L2 only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 and L3 only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L2 and L3 only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L3 only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 and L3 only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8489/gate2015-3-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 22,
          "question": "<p>For any two languages L1 and L2 such that L1 is context-free and L2 is recursively enumerable but not recursive, which of the following is/are necessarily true?<br>\nI. \\(\\bar{L_{1}}\\) (complement of L1) is recursive <br>\nII. \\( \\bar{L_{2}}\\) (complement of L2) is recursive <br>\nIII. \\(\\bar{L_{1}}\\) is context-free <br>\nIV. \\(\\bar{L_{1}} \\cup L_{2}\\) is recursively enumerable <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8019/gate2015-1-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 23,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages over the alphabet \\(\\sum =\\{0,1,c\\}:  \\)<br> \\(L_{1}=\\{0^{n}|1^{n}|n\\geq 0\\}\\)<br> \\(L_{2}=\\{wcw^{r}|w\\in \\{0,1\\}^{*}\\}\\) <br> \\(  L_{3}=\\{ww^{r}|w\\in \\{0,1\\}^{*}\\}\\) <br>Here \\(w^{r}\\) is the reverse of the string w. Which of these languages are deterministic Contextfree languages? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>None of the languages</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only L1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only L1 and L2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All the three languages</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Only L1 and L2</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2070/gate2014-3-36#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 24,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages. \\(L_{1}=\\{0^{p}1^{q}0^{r}|p,q,r\\geq 0\\}\\) <br> \\( L_{2}=\\{0^{p}1^{q}0^{r} | p,q,r \\geq  0, p \\neq  r \\}\\)<br> Which one of the following statements is FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L2 is context-free</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cap\\) L2 is context-free</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Complement of L2 is recursive.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Complement of L1 is context-free but not regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Complement of L1 is context-free but not regular</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1543/gate2013-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 25,
          "question": "<p>Consider the languages L1, L2 and L3 as given below <br>\n\\(L1=\\{0^{p}1^{q}|p,q\\in N\\}\\) <br> \\( L2=\\{0^{p}1^{q}|p,q\\in N and p=q\\} \\) and<br> \\(L3=\\{0^{p}1^{q}0^{r}|p,q,r\\in N \\; and \\; p=q=r\\}\\) <br>Which of the following statements is NOT TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Push Down Automata (PDA) can be used to recognize L1 and L2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 is a regular language</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>All the three languages are context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Turing machines can be used to recognize all the languages</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>All the three languages are context free</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2128/gate2011-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 26,
          "question": "<p>Consider the languages <br>\\(L1=\\{0^{i}1^{j}\\;| \\; i\\neq j\\}\\). <br>\\(L2=\\{0^{i}1^{j}\\;| \\; i=j\\}\\). <br>\\(L3=\\{0^{i}1^{j}\\;| \\; i=2j+1\\}\\).<br> \\(L4=\\{0^{i}1^{j}\\;| \\; i \\neq 2j\\}\\)<br> Which one of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only L2 is context free</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only L2 and L3 are context free</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only L1 and L3 are context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All are context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>All are context free</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2341/gate2010-40#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 27,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L=L_{1}\\cap L_{2}\\) , where \\(L_{1}\\) and \\(L_{2}\\) are languages as defined below: <br> \\(L_{1}= \\{a^{m}b^{m} c a^{n} b^{n}|m,n\\geq 0 \\}\\) <br> \\(L_{2}=\\{a^{i}b^{j}c^{k}|i,j,k\\geq 0 \\}\\)  <br><br> Then L is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Not recursive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Context free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Recursively enumerable but not context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Context free but not regular</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1326/gate2009-40#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 28,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages.<br>\n\\(L_1 = \\{a^i b^j c^k \\mid i = j, k \\geq 1\\}\\)<br>\n\\(L_2 = \\{a^i b^j \\mid j = 2i, i \\geq 0\\}\\)<br>\nWhich of the following is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not a CFL but \\(L_2\\) is</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap L_2 = \\varnothing\\) and \\(L_1\\) is non-regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup L_2\\) is not a CFL but \\(L_2\\) is</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>There is a 4-state PDA that accepts \\(L_1\\), but there is no DPDA that accepts \\(L_2\\).</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap L_2 = \\varnothing\\) and \\(L_1\\) is non-regular</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3343/gate2008-it-33\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 29,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is true for the language{ \\(a^{p}\\)|p is a prime} ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>It is not accepted by a Turing Machine</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>It is regular but not context-free</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>It is context-free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>It is neither regular nor context-free, but accepted by a Turing machine</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>It is neither regular nor context-free, but accepted by a Turing machine</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/407/gate2008-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 30,
          "question": "<p>The two grammars given below generate a language over the alphabet \\(\\{x, y, z\\}\\)<br>\nG1 :         \\(S \\rightarrow x \\mid z \\mid x \\ S \\mid z \\ S \\mid y \\ B\\) <br>\n\\(B \\rightarrow y \\mid z \\mid y \\ B \\mid z \\ B\\)<br>\nG2 :         \\(S \\rightarrow y \\mid z \\mid y \\ S \\mid z \\ S \\mid x \\ B\\)<br>\n\\(B \\rightarrow y \\mid y \\ S\\)<br>\nWhich one of the following choices describes the properties satisfied by the strings in these languages? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>G1 : No y appears before any x<br>\nG2 : Every x is followed by at least one y</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>G1 : No y appears before any x<br>\nG2 : No x appears before any y</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>G1 : No y appears after any x<br>\nG2 : Every x is followed by at least one y</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>G1 : No y appears after any x<br>\nG2 : Every y is followed by at least one x</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>G1 : No y appears before any x<br>\nG2 : Every x is followed by at least one y</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3481/gate2007-it-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 31,
          "question": "<p>The language \\(L=\\{0^{i}21^{i}|i\\geq 0\\}\\) over the alphabet {0,1,2} is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>not recursive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is recursive and is a deterministic CFL.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>is a regular language.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>is not a deterministic CFL but a CFL.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>is recursive and is a deterministic CFL.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1228/gate2007-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 32,
          "question": "<p>Let L be a context-free language and M a regular language. Then the language \\(L \\cap M\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>always regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>never regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>always a deterministic context-free language</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>always a context-free language</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>always a context-free language</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3571/gate2006-it-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 33,
          "question": "<p>Let  \\(L_{1}=\\{0^{n+m}1^{n}0^{m}|n,m\\geq 0\\}\\) <br> \\(L_{2}=\\{0^{n+m}1^{n+m}0^{m}|n,m\\geq 0\\}\\) <br> \\(L_{3}=\\{0^{n+m}1^{n+m}0^{n+m}|n,m\\geq 0\\}\\)<br> <br>Which of these languages are NOT context free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L3 only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L1 and L2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L2 and L3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>L2 and L3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/980/gate2006-19#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 34,
          "question": "<p>The language \\(\\{0^n 1^n 2^n \\mid 1 \\leq n \\leq 10^6\\}\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>context-free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>context-free but its complement is not context-free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>not context-free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>regular</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3751/gate2005-it-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 35,
          "question": "<p>Let L be a regular language and M be a context-free language, both over the alphabet \\(\\Sigma\\). Let \\(L^c\\) and \\(M^c\\) denote the complements of L and M respectively. Which of the following statements about the language  \\(L^c\\cup M^c\\) is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>It is necessarily regular but not necessarily context-free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>It is necessarily context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>It is necessarily non-regular.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3748/gate2005-it-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 36,
          "question": "<p>Consider the languages: <br><br>\\(L_{1}=\\{ww^{R}|w\\in \\{0,1\\}*\\} \\) <br>\\( L_{2}=\\{w\\#w^{R}|w\\in \\{0,1\\}*\\}\\),where # is a special symbol  <br>\\(  L_{3}=\\{ww|w\\in \\{0,1\\}*\\}\\)<br> <br>Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 is a deterministic CFL</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L2 is a deterministic CFL</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L3 is a CFL, but not a deterministic CFL</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L3 is a deterministic CFL</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>L2 is a deterministic CFL</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1380/gate2005-57#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 37,
          "question": "<p>Consider the languages: <br> \\(L_{1}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}c^{m}|n,m \\gt 0\\} \\) and \\(L_{2}=\\{a^{n}b^{m}c^{m}|n,m \\gt 0\\}\\)<br> Which one of the following statements is FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cap\\) L2 is a context-free language</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cup\\) L2 is a context-free language</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L1 and L2 are context-free language</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cap\\) L2 is a context sensitive language</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cap\\) L2 is a context-free language</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1378/gate2005-55#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 38,
          "question": "<p>The language {\\(a^{m}b^{n}c^{m+n}|m,n\\geq 1\\)} is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>context-free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>context sensitive but not context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>type-0 but not context sensitive</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>context-free but not regular</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1081/gate2004-87#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 39,
          "question": "<p>If the strings of a language L can be effectively enumerated in lexicographic (i.e.\nalphabetic) order, which of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L is necessarily finite</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L is regular but not necessarily finite</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L is context free but not necessarily regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L is recursive but not necessarily context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>L is recursive but not necessarily context free</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/120/gate2003-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 40,
          "question": "<p>The C language is : <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A context free language</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A context sensitive language</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A regular language</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Parsable fully only by a Turing machine</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>A context sensitive language</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/848/gate2002-2-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 41,
          "question": "<p>Let L denote the languages generated by the grammar \\(S \\to 0S0 \\mid 00\\).\nWhich of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L = 0^+\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L is regular but not \\(0^+\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L is context free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L is not context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>L is regular but not \\(0^+\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/628/gate2000-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 42,
          "question": "<p>If L1 is context free language and L2 is a regular language which of the following is/are false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1-L2 is not context free</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L1 \\cap L2\\) is context free</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\sim L1\\) is context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\sim L2\\) is regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L1-L2 is not context free</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1482/gate1999-2-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 43,
          "question": "<p>Context-free languages are closed under: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Union, intersection</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Union, Kleene closure</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Intersection, complement</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Complement, Kleene closure</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Union, Kleene closure</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1459/gate1999-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 44,
          "question": "<p>Define a context free languages \\(L \\in \\{0, 1\\}^*, \\text{init} (L) = \\{u \\mid uv \\in L\\) for some v in \\(\\{0, 1\\}^*\\}\\) ( in other words, \\(\\text{init}(L)\\) is the set of prefixes of L)<br>\nLet  \\(L = \\{w \\mid w \\text{ is nonempty and has an equal number of $0$'s and $1$'s}\\}\\)\nThen \\(\\text{init}(L)\\) is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings with unequal number of 0's and 1's</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings including null string</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings with exactly one more 0 than the number of 1's or one more 1 than the number of 0's</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings including null string</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2738/gate1996-2-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 45,
          "question": "<p>If \\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are context free languages and R a regular set, one of the languages below is not necessarily a context free language. Which one? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1.L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap R\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup L_2\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap L_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2737/gate1996-2-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 46,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following definitions below generate the same language as \\(L\\), where \\(L=\\{x^ny^n \\text{ such that } n\\geq 1 \\}\\)?<br>\nI.   \\(E \\rightarrow xEy\\mid xy\\)<br>\nII.  \\(x y \\mid (x^+xyy^+)\\)<br>\nIII. \\(x^+y^+\\)<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and II</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2632/gate1995-2-20\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 47,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements true ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>If a language is context free it can be always be accepted by a deterministic\npush-down automaton.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The union of two context free language is context free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The intersection of two context free language is context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The complement of a context free language is context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>The union of two context free language is context free.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/698/gate2001-1-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 48,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only:<br>\nContext-free languages are: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>closed under union</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>closed under complementation</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>closed under intersection</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>closed under Kleene closure</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>closed under union</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/572/gate1992-02-xix\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 49,
          "question": "<p>Context-free languages and regular languages are both closed under the operation (s) of : <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1989)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Union</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Intersection</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Concatenation</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Complementation</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Union</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/87117/gate1989-3-ii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}